Guide to the John Ruskin Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Correspondence, 1829-1949; Series I
  - Letters from John Ruskin to Individuals identified only by First Name or Title
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "Dear Gordan." No place., undated (Box 11)
      Bought from Winifred A. Myers (Autographs) Ltd. on the Library Associates Fund, 1959 April 5
    - Autograph note, signed, to "My dear Griffith." No place., undated (Box 11)
      Bought from Clive Farahar and Sophie Dupre on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 2001 October 8
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "Dear Harry." Liverpool., 1878 November 10 (Box 11)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "Darling Julia." Brantwood, Coniston, Lancashire., undated (Box 11)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "Dear Laing." No place., undated (Box 11)
      Bought from Clive Farahar and Sophie Dupre as a bequest of Harry T. Mercer, Yale 1924, and Dorothy N. Mercer, for use of the Tinker Library, 1995 February 10
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "My dear Lillian." Brantwood, Coniston, Lancashire., 1879 May 14 (Box 11)
      Bought from Gerard A. J. Stodolski, Inc. on the George Henry Nettleton Fund, 1996 March 26
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "Dear [Norm?]." [London]., [1857 December 4] (Box 11)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "My dear Parry." No place., [1859?] (Box 11)
      Bought from C. A. Stonehill on the Plain Fund, 1944
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "My dear Patmore." Brantwood, Coniston, Lancashire., 1876 July 7 (Box 11)
    - 11 autograph letters, signed, to "Ruthie," Ruskin's nurse, and 1 autograph letter, signed, to "Brownie," her sister. Various places., 1882-1883 (Box 11)
      Bought from C. A. Stonehill on the Library Associates Fund, 1947 January 6
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "My dear Scott." No place., undated (Box 11)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "My dearest S." Lucca., 1874 September 24 (Box 11)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "My dearest S." No place., 1875 December 27 (Box 11)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "My dearest S." Brantwood, Coniston, Lancashire., [1877 October] (Box 11)
    - 3 autograph letters, signed, to "My dearest S." Brantwood, no place, Herne Hill., 1878 April 15, 1879 November 10, 1879 December 6 (Box 11)
    - 7 autograph letters, signed, to "Susie." Brantwood, Coniston, Lancashire, various places., 1879-1884, undated (Box 11)
      Accompanied by an autograph letter, signed, from [W. G.] to Mrs. Lyttleton, Ambleside, 1909 November 28.
      Bought from William Reese Co. on the Library Associates Fund, 2001 October 24
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "Dear Theodore." Brantwood, Coniston, Lancashire., 1886 December 2 (Box 11)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "My dear Willie." Edinburgh., [no year] September 10 (Box 11)
  - Letters from John Ruskin to Unidentified Individuals
    - Autograph note to an unidentified correspondent. No place., [1857 February 4] (Box 12)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "My dear sir." Oxford., 1857 July 4 (Box 12)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "Sir." Denmark Hill., 1860 November 27 (Box 12)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "My dear sir." No place., 1861 (postmark) (Box 12)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "My dear sir." Baden, Argovie, Switzerland., 1863 October 29 (Box 12)
      Gift of Herman W. Liebert, 1958 February
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "My dear boys." Lauffenbourg, Rhine., 1863 November 9 (Box 12)
      Accompanied by manuscript of "Enmity and Envy", corrected, circa 1863.
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "My dear sir." Denmark Hill., 1864 July 12 (Box 12)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "My dear sir." Denmark Hill., [1867 March 4] (Box 12)
    - 2 autograph letters, signed, to "My dear sir." Denmark Hill., 1868 February 5, undated (Box 12)
      With drafts of replies in pencil on verso of each letter.
      Bought from Clive Farahar and Sophie Dupre on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 1998 January 9
    - Draft of an autograph letter addressed to "Gentlemen." Oxford., 1870 May 23 (Box 12)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "My dear sir." Denmark Hill., 1871 September 5 (Box 12)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "My dear sir." Ravenna., 1872 July 15 (Box 12)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "My dear madam." Coniston, Lancashire., 1875 September 7 (Box 12)
      Anonymous Fund, 1971
    - Autograph letter in third person to an unidentified correspondent. Herne Hill., 1876 March 31 (Box 12)
      Accompanied by an envelope addressed to "Prince Leopold" in an unidentified hand.
    - 3 autograph letters, signed, to an unidentified artist. Venice., 1877 April 17, 24, 30 (Box 12)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "My dear madam." Brantwood, Coniston, Lancashire., 1878 May 14 (Box 12)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "My dear sir." Lancashire., 1879 March 15 (Box 12)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "My dear sir." [London]., 1882 February 10 (Box 12)
      Accompanied by a typed letter, signed, from Gabriel Wells Royce to Chauncey B. Tinker, 1937 March 1.
      Accompanied by a catalogue entry.
      Bought on the Library Associates Fund, 1937 March
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "My dear sir." Sheffield., 1882 July 19 (Box 12)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "My dear boy." Brantwood., 1883 June 23 (Box 12)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "Sir." Brantwood, Coniston, Lancashire., 1883 December 14 (Box 12)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "Gentlemen." Denmark Hill, Camberwell., [circa 1846] January 21 (Box 12)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "Gentlemen." No place., [1855] (Box 12)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "My dear madam." Oxford., [1870?] (Box 12)
      Accompanied by catalogue entry.
      Bought from Maggs Brothers Ltd. with the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 1978 May 26
    - Fragment of an autograph letter, signed, to an unidentified correspondent. No place., [circa 1890] (Box 12)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "My dear sir." Lancashire., [no year] March 23 (Box 12)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "My dear sir." Northwich., [no year] October 15 (Box 12)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "My dear sir." Oxford., [no year] November 13 (Box 12)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "My dear madam." No place., undated (Box 12)
      Accompanied by a postcard of John Ruskin.
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "My dear sir." No place., undated (Box 12)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "My dear sir." No place., undated (Box 12)
    - Autograph letter in third person to an unidentified correspondent. Brantwood, Coniston, Lancashire., undated (Box 12)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "My dear sir." Brantwood, Coniston, Lancashire., undated (Box 12)
      Bought from Clive Farahar and Sophie Dupre on the Edwin J. Beinecke Fund, 1997 March 19
    - Fragment of an autograph letter, signed, to an unidentified correspondent. No place., undated (Box 12)
      Bought from Clive Farahar and Sophie Dupre on the Starling W. Childs Library Fund, 1997 April 17
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "My dear sir." No place., undated (Box 12)
      Bought from David J. Holmes on the Starling W. Childs Library Fund, 1998 March 27
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "Sir." Denmark Hill., undated (Box 12)
      Accompanied by a cabinet photograph of John Ruskin.
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "My dear sir." No place., undated (Box 12)
      Bought from C. A. Stonehill on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 1965 January 5
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "My dear sir." Denmark Hill., undated (Box 12)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "My dear sir." No place., undated (Box 12)
      Gift of the estate of Katherine Dreier, 1953
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "My dear Mr. __." No place., undated (Box 12)
    - Fragment of an autograph letter, signed, to an unidentified correspondent. No place., undated (Box 12)
      Bought from Clive Farahar and Sophie Dupre on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 2002 December 31
    - 5 fragments of autograph letters, signed, to unidentified correspondents. No place., undated (Box 12)
    - 6 envelopes addressed to the following individuals: Henry S. King (2), Robert Thompson (2), W. Hale White (1), William Sherlock (1). Some in Ruskin's hand., 1872-1887, undated (Box 12)
      Bought by Chauncey B. Tinker, 1930
  - Letters to John Ruskin
    - Hewetson, Henry Bendelack (1849-1899). Autograph letter, signed, to John Ruskin. Leeds., [18??] August (Box 13)
      Accompanied by a clipping from the London Daily News.
      Bought from Goodspeed's Book Shop, Inc. by Professor C. B. Tinker, 1930 November 6
    - Ruskin, Margaret Cox (Cock) (1781–1871). Autograph letter, signed, to son, John Ruskin. Denmark Hill., 1864 June 9 (Box 13)
      Bought from Winifred A. Myers (Autographs) Ltd. on the William Lyon Phelps Memorial Fund, 1956 October 2
    - Ruskin, Margaret Cox (Cock) (1781–1871). 2 autograph letters, signed, to son, John Ruskin. Denmark Hill., 1866 May 28, 1866 June 6 (Box 13)
      Includes an envelope addressed to "Miss Alexander" with manuscript note.
  - Third Party Correspondence
    - Adam, Robert Borthwick. Correspondence and bills from various booksellers to Adam, relating to Ruskin material. Various places., 1894-1929 (Box 13)
    - Brown, Rawdon. 2 autograph letters, signed, to "Dear Panezzi", and 1 autograph letter, signed, to "Mr. Dempster". Venice, no place., 1869 April 3, 14, undated (Box 13)
    - Conway, William. Autograph letter, signed with initials, to his mother. Liverpool., [1887?] (Box 13)
    - Poyser, M. A. Autograph letter, signed with initials, to "My dearest Mother". [London]., 1859 December 12 (Box 13)
      Accompanied by an autograph letter, signed, from W. Griscome to J. T. Babb, London, 1939 May 20.
      Accompanied by a clipping from an auction catalogue.
      Bought from C. A. Stonehill on the Library Associates Fund, 1939 April
    - Sharp, F. J. 3 autograph letters, signed, to Chauncey B. Tinker. Lancashire., 1949 February 21, March 30, May 3 (Box 13)
      Accompanied by a manuscript copy in Sharp's hand of a letter from Charles E. Goodspeed to Sharp, 1949 April 15
      Accompanied by a typed copy of a letter from Chauncey B. Tinker to F. J. Sharp, 1949 March 15
      Accompanying the letter of 1949 May 3 are a photograph of Ruskin and an impression of his father's seal.
    - Stevens, B. F., and Brown. Letters, telegrams, and other material to Charles Goodspeed relating to his purchases of John Ruskin material., 1931 May 4-1933 May 16 (Box 13)
      Gift of Charles Goodspeed, 1944
      Accompanied by an auction catalogue, 1931
      Accompanied by invoices and a few carbon copies of letters from Charles Goodspeed.
    - Stevens, B. F., and Brown. Auction catalogues sent to Charles Goodspeed relating to his purchases of John Ruskin material., 1930 July 24, 1931 May 20, 1931 July 15-16 (Box 13)
      Accompanied by a catalogue from Goodspeed's Book Shop of paintings, drawings, and manuscripts of John Ruskin, no. 211. 2 copies.
    - Stevens, B. F., and Brown. 3 pamphlets on Brantwood, originally accompanying other Stevens and Brown material., 1932, 1935, undated (Box 13)
    - Wallet, Henry. Autograph letter, signed, to William Conway. Arnold House., 1887 April 4 (Box 13)
- Manuscripts, 1826-1897; Series II
  Series II, Manuscripts, has been arranged into two subseries: Bound Manuscripts and Notebooks; and Unbound Manuscripts.
  - Bound Manuscripts and Notebooks
    - Architectural Notebook - Manuscript notebook with sketches and diagrams in pencil and ink. Italy., 1850-1851; (1 volume) (Box 14)
      Bought by C. B. Tinker, 1930
    - The Blue Pimpernell - Autograph manuscript. Bound in leather., undated; (1 volume) (Box 14)
      Bound together with The Purple Dead-Nettle, The Snow-Drop, and The Toad.
    - Christ Entering Jerusalem - Autograph manuscript. 1p. In green case., undated; (1 volume) (Box 14)
      Accompanied by an autograph note, signed, from John Ruskin to Charles Eliot Norton. [London]. [1873 February]. With manuscript notes by Norton. Together with an envelope and an etching of John Ruskin.
      Accompanied by an autograph note, signed with initials, from John Ruskin to "Colvin". Brantwood, Coniston. 1872 March 5.
      Bought on the Frank Altschul Fund, 1939
      Accompanied by 2 envelopes, addressed in Ruskin's hand, to Sir Arthur Helps and to Mr. Francis Butler.
      Accompanied by an autograph note, signed with initials, from John Ruskin to "My true Charles". No place, undated.
    - The Elements of Drawing - Two sets of proofs, with manuscript corrections in Ruskin's hand., undated (Box 15)
    - The Ethics of the Dust - Original autograph manuscript. Bound in green morocco., undated; (1 volume) (Box 15)
      Bound together with the manuscript of the lecture on war from "The Crown of Wild Olive".
      Bound together with the manuscripts of three lectures on "The Cestus of Aglaia".
      Bought on the Frank Altschul Fund, 1933
    - Fiction Fair and Foul - Original autograph manuscript. Bound in crimson morocco., undated; (1 volume) (Box 16)
    - Flora, Called First Flora - Manuscript notebook with pen and ink sketches, indexed., 1866; (1 volume) (Box 16)
    - Flora, Called Second - Manuscript notebook with pen and ink sketches, indexed., undated; (1 volume) (Box 16)
      Bound together with first drafts of chapters 1 and 4 of Proserpina.
      Gift of Chauncey Brewster Tinker, 1930
    - Flora, Called Third - Manuscript notebook with pen and ink sketches, indexed., undated; (1 volume) (Box 17)
      Bound together with first drafts of chapters 2 and 3 of Proserpina.
    - Fors Clavigera - Original holograph manuscript of portions of Letter 82, and autograph corrected galleys of Letter 67. Bound in brown levant morocco., undated; (1 volume) (Box 35 (Oversize))
      Bound together with 2 portraits of John Ruskin, one from a photograph by Elliot & Fry published by J. F. Dexter, 1884, one by Sir J. E. Millais, from The Magazine of Art.
      Bound together with 19 autograph letters, signed, from John Ruskin to Susanna Miller. Various places. [1875?]-1887, undated. Includes 10 envelopes.
      Bound together with 10 autograph letters, signed, from John Ruskin to Frederick Harris. Brantwood, Coniston, Lancashire. 1885-1887, undated.
      Bound together with an autograph letter, signed, from John Ruskin to Mr. Blewitt. Brantwood, Coniston, Lancashire. 1883 April 1.
      Bound together with 2 autograph letters, signed, from John Ruskin to unidentified correspondents. Brantwood, Coniston, Lancashire. [no year] December 28, [no year] January 21.
      Bought from C. A. Stonehill on the Library Associates Fund, 1944
    - Harry and Lucy, Poems, etc. - Four small leather-bound notebooks and one stitched in a paper cover, containing notes, poems, and drawings. In a blue morocco slip-case., 1826-1829 (Box 17)
      One notebook contains John James Ruskin's list of John Ruskin's published verses, and "Eudosia."
      Bought from Goodspeed's Book Shop, Inc., 1930
    - Home Flora - Manuscript notebook with pen and ink sketches., undated; (1 volume) (Box 17)
      Contains part of chapters 2 and 3 of Proserpina, as well as a draft of the rule of St. George's Guild at the end of the volume.
    - Iteriad, etc. - Large notebook containing manuscripts of "Iteriad" and other poems, including "The Gipsies". Bound in blue morocco, in a blue morocco slip-case., undated; (1 volume) (Box 18)
      Bound together with a prose essay, a reply to a critique on J. M. W. Turner, published in Blackwood's Magazine.
    - Juvenilia - Three small leather-bound notebooks, containing boyhood notes on geology, history, Latin, and Ruskin's travels. In a blue morocco slip-case., undated (Box 18)
    - The King of the Golden River - Autograph manuscript. Bound in blue morocco., undated; (1 volume) (Box 18)
      Includes title page and manuscript notes by Alexander Wedderburn.
    - La Madonna Dell' Acqua - Autograph manuscript, signed with initials. Bound in red morocco., undated; (1 volume) (Box 18)
      Bound together with "The Tears of Psammenitus", autograph manuscript, signed with initials.
      Bought on the Library Associates Fund, 1956
    - Lectures in Val d'Arno - Autograph manuscript., undated; (1 volume) (Box 19)
      Bought from Goodspeed's Book Shop, Inc. by Chauncey B. Tinker, 1930 November 6
    - Lectures on Florentine Artists - Autograph manuscript of the Oxford lectures. Bound in red cloth., 1874; (1 volume) (Box 19)
      Bought on the Frank Altschul Fund, 1936 May 29
    - Lectures on Landscape - Autograph manuscript of the Oxford lectures. Bound in 3/4 leather., undated; (1 volume) (Box 19)
      Bound together with manuscripts of other lectures.
    - Miscellaneous Notebooks - 5 manuscript notebooks., undated; (5 volumes) (Box 20)
      The notebooks are arranged and numbered as follows:
      1. Pencil account of the Pass from Sestri to Florence
      2. Notes on Chaucer, The Flower and The Leaf and The Dream.
      3. Notes on Homer, Pindar, etc. with list of 23 liturgical manuscripts in Ruskin's possession.
      4. Catalogue of the books in Ruskin's library, with manuscript account for R. Talling laid in.
      5. Geological notebook with pen and ink sketches.
      6. Geological notebook with pen and ink sketches.
      7. Geological notebook with pen and ink sketches.
      8. Geological notebook with pen and ink sketches.
      9. Historical and classical notebook.
      10. Historical and classical notebook.
      11. Historical and classical notebook.
      12. Historical and classical notebook.
      13. Historical and classical notebook.
      Bought from Goodspeed's Book Shop, Inc. by Chauncey B. Tinker, 1930
    - Miscellaneous Notebooks (continued) - 5 manuscript notebooks., undated; (5 volumes) (Box 21)
    - Miscellaneous Notebooks (continued) - 3 manuscript notebooks., undated; (3 volumes) (Box 22)
    - Modern Painters - Page proofs of Volume IV, Part V, "Of Mountain Beauty", with manuscript corrections. In an orange half-morocco box case., undated; (1 volume) (Box 22)
      Bought from C. A. Stonehill on the Library Associates Fund, 1948 January 8
    - Modern Painters - Page proofs of Volume V, Part IV, "Of Leaf Beauty". In an orange half-morocco box case., undated; (1 volume) (Box 23)
      Together with Unto This Last - Page proofs of Part IV, "Ad Valorem", with manuscript corrections.
      Together with "An Inquiry into Some of the Conditions at Present Affecting the Study of Architecture in our Schools" - Page proofs with manuscript corrections.
    - "The Mystery of Life and its Arts" - Autograph manuscript with corrections and alterations. Bound in blue morocco., [1868]; (1 volume) (Box 23)
      "The Mystery of Life and its Arts," a lecture delivered in the theater of the Royal College of Science, Dublin, 1868, was later included in the revised edition of Sesame and Lilies, 1871.
      Includes bookplates of Alexander Wedderburn and E. H. Mills.
      Bought from James F. Drake on the Albert H. Childs Fund, 1943 September 21
    - Notebook - Manuscript notebook with water-colors, sketches, and drawings. Bound in purple full calf., 1842 May-September; (1 volume) (Box 23)
      Includes an autograph letter, signed, from John Ruskin to Charles Eliot Norton, presenting him with the book and apologizing for its condition. Oxford. 1872 December 24. Includes envelope.
      Gift of Mr. and Mrs. Arnold Whitridge (Library Associates). Bought by them from Miss Elizabeth G. Norton, 1936.
      Towards the end of the volume are notes for a Horticultural Society, dated 1846 January 20
    - Oxford Lectures - Autograph manuscript. Bound in red cloth., undated; (1 volume) (Box 24)
    - Poems, 1829-1832 - Notebook containing miscellaneous poetry in manuscript. In a blue morocco slip-case., (1 volume) (Box 24)
      Bound together with pages of The Battle of Waterloo, a drama.
    - Poems, 1833 - Notebook containing the manuscript and pen and ink sketches of a poem Ruskin composed while on a Continental trip. In a blue morocco slip-case., (1 volume) (Box 24)
      Includes clipping of a catalogue entry on the first flyleaf.
    - Poems, 1831-1838 - Notebook containing poetry, prose, and drawings, some finished, others fragmentary or drafts. In a blue morocco slip-case., (1 volume) (Box 25)
    - The Political Economy of Art: Being the Substance of Two Lectures... - Page proofs with manuscript corrections. In an orange half-morocco box case., 1857; (1 volume) (Box 25)
    - Praeterita - Autograph manuscript of most of the work. Bound in black cloth. Volume I of 6., undated; (1 volume) (Box 26)
      The three octavo volumes of the Diary cover 1885 January 1-July 14. The three folio volumes consist of autograph copies, corrected proofs, and some copies in a secretary's hand. The third volume contains the Dilecta.
      The volumes went through a fire while in the possession of Charles E. Goodspeed, and are, in consequence, waterstained and charred. The text is not badly damaged.
      Includes 2 typed letters, signed, from Charles Goodspeed to C. B. Tinker, regarding the manuscript. 1941 March 25 and 31.
      Gift of Charles E. Goodspeed
    - Praeterita - Autograph manuscript of most of the work. Bound in black cloth. Volume II of 6., undated; (1 volume) (Box 27)
    - Praeterita - Autograph manuscript of most of the work. Bound in black cloth. Volumes III and IV of 6., undated; (2 volumes) (Box 28)
    - Praeterita - Autograph manuscript of most of the work. Bound in black cloth. Volumes V and VI of 6., undated; (2 volumes) (Box 29)
    - Proserpina - Autograph manuscript of part of Proserpina, with some pages of corrected proof., undated (Box 29)
    - Proserpina - Autograph manuscript of much of the second volume, with some corrected page proofs, and drawings by Ruskin in the text. Bound in red cloth., undated; (1 volume) (Box 30)
      Some of this manuscript was not used in the printed book.
      From the Brantwood collection of Ruskin manuscripts sold at Sotheby's, 1931.
      Bought on the Library Associates Fund, 1931
    - Readings in Modern Painters - Autograph manuscript of the Oxford lectures. Bound in red cloth., 1877; (1 volume) (Box 30)
      Bought on the Frank Altschul Fund 1936 May 29
    - Sesame and Lilies - Page proofs of Part I, Lecture I, "Of King's Treasuries", with manuscript corrections. In an orange half-morocco slip case., undated; (1 volume) (Box 30)
    - Sesame and Lilies - Galley proofs of Part II, Lecture II, "Of Queens' Gardens", with manuscript corrections. Bound in orange half-morocco., undated; (1 volume) (Box 35 (Oversize))
    - The Stones of Venice - Printed pages (1874 edition) with autograph manuscript revisions and additions made for the Travellers' edition. Bound in red morocco., [1879-1881] (Box 30)
      Also includes four leaves of a galley proof with autograph revisions and additions made for Chapter 4 of Volume II of the Travellers' edition.
      From the James M. Osborn Collection, 1951
  - Unbound Manuscripts
    - The Art of England - Page proofs of Lecture V with manuscript corrections., [1883] (Box 31)
      The edges of the pages are charred, affecting the text.
    - Bank notes (2) - signed by Ruskin, 1869 September 16, 1870 June 24 (Box 31)
    - Calais - Manuscript, in prose, together with Passing the Alps., undated (Box 31)
      The pages are water-damaged.
    - Conversation Supposed to be Held Between Mr. R., Mrs. R., Miss R., and Master R., on New Year's Morning, 1836 - Autograph manuscript. (Box 31)
      Mounted on stubs, with charred edges, affecting text.
    - Dilecta - Autograph manuscript fragment, together with autograph manuscript fragment of Praeterita., undated (Box 31)